<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A brown dozen of drunkards: (ali-ass drink-hards) whipt, and shipt to the Isle of Gulls: for their abusing of Mr. Malt the bearded son, and Barley-broth the brainlesse daughter of Sir John Barley-corne. All joco-seriously descanted to our wine-drunk, wrath-drunk, zeale-drunk, staggering times. By one that hath drunk at S. Patricks well.</title>
            <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95524</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T435</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E451_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203750</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863586</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863586</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161930</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95524)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161930)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E451[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A brown dozen of drunkards: (ali-ass drink-hards) whipt, and shipt to the Isle of Gulls: for their abusing of Mr. Malt the bearded son, and Barley-broth the brainlesse daughter of Sir John Barley-corne. All joco-seriously descanted to our wine-drunk, wrath-drunk, zeale-drunk, staggering times. By one that hath drunk at S. Patricks well.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, John, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Robert Austin on Adlin-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>One that hath drunk at S. Patricks well = John Taylor.</note>
                  <note>With a title-page woodcut. The words "wine-drunk, .. zeale-drunk," are enclosed in brackets on title page.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf bears verse: The authors friend to every sober and solid reader.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy (recto of first leaf): "July 6th 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Drinking of alcoholic beverages --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161930:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Brown Dozen of Drunkards: (Ali-aſs Drink-hards) <hi>Whipt, and ſhipt to the Jſle of Gulls:</hi> For their abuſing of Mr. <hi>Malt</hi> the bearded ſon, and <hi>Barley-broth</hi> the brainleſſe daughter of Sir <hi>John Barley-corne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All joco-ſeriouſly deſcanted to our
<list>
                  <item>Wine-drunk, </item>
                  <item>Wrath-drunk,</item>
                  <item>Zeale-drunk,</item>
               </list> ſtaggering Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By one that hath drunk at</hi> S. Patricks <hi>Well.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of drunkards</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Auſtin</hi> on <hi>Adlin-hill.</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161930:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161930:2"/>
            <head>A browne dozen of Drunkards, ali-aſs Drink-hards, Jocoſeriouſly deſcanted to our wine-drunk, wrath-drunk and zeale-drunk ſtaggering cimes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>1. <hi>Drunken Wimble-tree, ali-aſs Reeler.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe fore-man of the Jury to give in their verdict at <hi>Bacchus</hi> his Barre, that a full pot is better then an empty purſe: make way for him there, let him have elbow-roome enough; mark how how he comes rowling like a wheelbarrow, wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring like a Greenland Whale, and tumbling like a ſhip amongſt Waves, half under water: look at him well (as an embleme of our Perniz'd times, as good as any in <hi>Catz, Quarles, Whitney,</hi> or <hi>Withers,</hi>) how he turnes round like a ball, or an unbiaſſed bowle, runs in a circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar motion, like a Scopperill, or Whirligigg, as though more quick-ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were in his heels, then ſilver in his purſe; and more weathercock on his head, then wit in his head: how naturally his feet without any art, like a poetizing louſe, with ſix feet, make Hexameters with Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meters, long and ſhort, up and downe, like the ſpoaks in the whirling wheels of thoſe Coaches, in which <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> was drawne by the pampered Jades of Aſia: By the influence of the Moone on his maulted Element, one would think this Moon-calfe, like other calves, had the ſturdie, or like a Smithfield Jade, the ſtaggers, he takes ſuch frisks and capers from the circumference of the wide ſtreets, into the center of the channell, which he claimes as his hereditary right, by ſuch a title as the Rebells kept a plot of ground neere Athy in Ireland, called Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes Green, from whence they oft marched (as <hi>Campian, Garnet,</hi> and other Jeſuites, from Tyber to Tyburne) downe Gallowes-gate, and up Hempſtreet: he is ſo intoxicated in his giddy braines like a Midſummers Gooſe, that he ſtaggers in his motions, like our old and new Enthuſiaſts, Familiſts; Anabablers once in Germany, and now in England, with our new Seekers for the Man in the Moon drinking Claret, reeling in their motions, and miſcreant opinions, as once drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Elderton</hi> in his Potions: I will ſtand to it, that however he goes to the Ale-ſtand a Nowne Subſtantive, he ever comes from it a Nowne Adje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive, no more able to ſtand by himſelfe, then a hop or a vine without a prop or a wall: a trencher-Paraſite without a feeding Patrone, or a weaning child without the upholding hand of a mother, or a nurſe;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161930:3"/>take your hand from him, and let him ſtand on his owne leggs, and you take crutches from a cripple, and a leaning ſtaffe or poſt from a lame Giles, knockt in the head with a Barly bullet, as an Oxe with a Butchers Axe, <hi>procumbit humi bos,</hi> he ſtands ſo long as he can ſtand, then ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and falls, <hi>per varios caſus,</hi> after he hath declined <hi>potum,</hi> (to which he is much inclined) throughout all caſes, till he be fit to be truſt up in a cap-caſe, <hi>tendit in lutum,</hi> he reels into the mire, where he wallowes like a weake horſe in a bog, or a Gentleman in debt, and cannot get out, till ſome charitable hand help him: To anatomize him further, this Brute-aſſe (though not ſo oraculouſly as <hi>Brutus</hi>) oft kiſſeth his Mother earth, and acknowledgeth her bowell-bred wormes to be his brothers, yea with as much humility, as once S. <hi>Francis</hi> ſaid brother Wolfe, he oft ſaith brother Hog, ſince it cannot be denied, but that as the ſame Barley-graines feed and fat them both, ſo they are oft ſtied to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and kennelled in one channell, which although he lift his leggs oft verie high, when his head goes very low, it's very probable, that he is as full of grave thoughts, or thoughts of his grave, as a Gooſe egge long ſitten full of matter, ſince he is ſo oft digging his grave, as the Badger his hole, with his very noſe, onely his pride is, that after he hath kept his <hi>priorums</hi> amongſt his Ariſtippized pot-profeſſors, he cauſeth the ſtones, as once <hi>Tarlton,</hi> to kiſſe his <hi>poſteriornms,</hi> though they be the bones of his old mother <hi>Tellus,</hi> as Poets tell us: the thing I moſt pity in him is this, that for all the reeling of this Ganderized giddy head, if his wife card no better at home, then he reels abroad, they will make a web no better then <hi>Arachnes</hi> clew, fit to be ſwept down, or then a fooles Medley of Goates wool, Doggs haire, and moſſie downe; they will twiſt ſuch webs as <hi>Penelope</hi> and <hi>Lucrece</hi> wove <hi>ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendas Graecas,</hi> in <hi>Platoes</hi> great year, when all Hens will make holy wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, all Virgin veſtall Nuns give milk, all Judges hate bribes, all Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>year refuſe fees, and all Black-coats great benefices: but ſince it is as probable that he may reel home, to ſteale a nap, as ſome Senior or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior Immerito may be informed in theſe reformed times, how to ſlip, ſteale, or ſtumble into an undeſerved plump perſonage, we will leave him to lolling, till his wine be out of his head, and his wit in, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flex on his next fellow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>2. <hi>Drink-hard Helluoh.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Toſpottalian of a ſtronger bulk and braine then the former wind (or wine) ſhaken reed, or any of his fellowes: one that is no flincher,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161930:3"/>he will ſtand to it more then any Tinker, as a metall'd man indeed, back and edge; he will not out, till the laſt man be born, nor ſhrinke from his tippling taske, (like moſt now a daies from their poor friends) like Weſterne cloth in the wetting, he is not looſe in the haft, like ſo many Totnams that have lately turned French, yea Hiſpanioliz'd, Italionate, or Devills incarnate for their own ends, if he ſet his feet once at <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> his Barre, he cannot be peerkt over as a wrangler, he will goe thorow ſtitch with his work in ſucking <hi>Bacchus</hi> his grapes, till they be as dry as a kimeſtick, or the ſparks in a ſmiths throat: he will not fall off, as a Horſe-Leach from ſucking the Gouty leggs of a <hi>Gundimer,</hi> when ſhe is full, or as a Souldierly <hi>Clineas,</hi> or <hi>Dametas</hi> from his co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, when his faint heart is in his heels: he is a ſtiffe blade indeed, ſteele to the very back, yea to give this doughty Drunkard (like the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill) his due, though I ſet him in the ſecond place to his ſmall grace, as though it were ſomething, as in the Olimpick Games, to be a ſecond in wraſtling, as the Pitcher-bangers in <hi>Alexanders</hi> Feaſt at Babylon, for the Barly wreath and <hi>Bacchus</hi> his Garland, yet indeed he is like a Cock of the game amongſt Famlerts, or a Conqueror amongſt Cravens, the King and Cob of all the reſt, uſually a Ledger when they are all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der board; no Beere Brewers horſe hath the commendation to draw on, (draw in) or beare his drinke better then he: as there is <hi>fama in malo,</hi> fame even in infamy, (which he aimed at, who burnt <hi>Diana's</hi> Temple) ſo like theſe furre-blazed Bacchanalians in their times, <hi>Tricon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius, Novengius, Bonoſus, Tymoleon,</hi> and the reſt of the riotors, he is the <hi>Coripheus</hi> and prime amongſt all the frothy fraternity of Fudlers, the proto-Lippler amongſt all his <hi>Naballs,</hi> his <hi>Nebuloes,</hi> his drunken neighbours, the maine barrell amongſt leſſer firkins, in which he ſteeps his Lands monies and meanes, till both he and his be in a pitifull pickle; he hath a drunken Dropſie in his throat harder to be quenched with wine, then the Golden Dropſie in a covetous <hi>Cremes,</hi> or then the flames in the Northern Hecla, the Scicilian Aetna, or that <hi>Veſuvius</hi> which choaked <hi>Pliny,</hi> to be quenched with water; harder to be cured then the Gout, the Sciatica, the Strangury, or the regnant ſpleen amongſt Sectaries of all ſorts and ſexes: yea as dangerous, ſo no leſſe difficult to be cured, then the ſhaking of the elbow in an habituated Gameſter, the hot mouth Feaver in a ſcold, the tongue Palſie in a babbling <hi>Battus,</hi> the ſtone in the heart, worſe then in the reines of Pharoized impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, his Appetite for drink; is like the grave for bodies, hell for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161930:4"/>ſonles, <hi>materia prima</hi> for formes, the fire for fuell, and the barren womb of a <hi>Meſſalina</hi> for luſt, which was <hi>laſſata non ſatiata,</hi> inſatiable, as <hi>Pliny</hi> the younger, <hi>Plautus, Cleanthes, Demoſthenes,</hi> and others in their Diurnall, and nocturnall ſtudies, were <hi>Helluobs (Librorum)</hi> of Books, ſo he is <hi>Helluoh liquidorum,</hi> of bottles filled with liquids, <hi>quo plus bibuntur, plus ſitiuntur aquae,</hi> the more he drinks, more dry he is, like the Smiths forge, ſaith <hi>Leonius,</hi> (<hi>de Morbis lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. <hi>ſect.</hi> 3.) which by an Antipariſtaſis burnes more fiercely by caſting water on it, like un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>leckt lime: liquids rather inflame him, then cool him, I know no diſeaſe more ſpread over millions of <hi>Microcoſmes,</hi> like a Canker, more domineering, more incapable of cure, then this ſwelling Gangrene, or a ſwilling drinking Dropſie, except a Tympany of more then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian, even Luceferian pride in many Sectaries.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>3. <hi>Of drunken Barnabee.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WIth whom to make a ſhort diſpatch, and to truſſe up his humor in a paper halter, becauſe we have dwelt too long upon <hi>Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luoh,</hi> this <hi>Barnabee,</hi> ali-aſs Maudlin drunk, beſides the deſcription that his proper new Ballad makes of him, as <hi>drunke all night and dry in the morning,</hi> his carch being ſtill one tooth is dry, like one old <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berlaine,</hi> called old <hi>Twitcher</hi> in Yorkſhire, who though he had waſhed many hundred pounds downe his throat, proteſted he was yet dry for all that: but paſſing by that humour, which hath ſome coincidence with <hi>Helluohs,</hi> this our maultified Maudlin is but halfe drunk and half ſober, like a Newter in Religion, halfe a Proteſtant, half a Papiſt, halfe light, halfe darkneſſe, like the twi-light, or as a luke-warme Laodicean profeſſor, half hot, half cold, or indeed his true Hierogliphick is an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chized, Tarltonized <hi>Buffon,</hi> half a fool, half a knave, like a mule, half a horſe, halfe an aſſe, or a Cynocephaliſt, halfe a dog, half an ape, or a Mare-maid, half fiſh halfe fleſh, <hi>(Mulier formoſa ſupernè deſinens in piſcem,</hi>) but chiefly reflecting on <hi>Virgils</hi> worſe verſe, as a Ventriloquiſt termed <hi>his ſemivirum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> bovem, ſemibovem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> virum,</hi> half a man in his ſober part, halfe an Oxe, a very beaſt in his acted drunken poſtures, juſt (or unjuſt) as King <hi>Philip</hi> was on his Tribunall, half aſleep, half awake, not as a Lion, the embleme of a Polititian, waking when he feignes to ſleep, as that <hi>Witt-all,</hi> or all-wit, in Rome did to <hi>Mecoenas:</hi> (with his <hi>ſoli Mecoenati dormio</hi>) but like a Semidormant, and Semivigilant, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt hawke and buzzard, cup and can, a Semi-drunkard, and Semi-ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beratus, quoth old <hi>Horſley,</hi> like a meer mongrill, halfe a Gray-hound,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161930:4"/>halfe a Maſtife: yet as in Divinity we ſay, that God will have all in man or nought, the whole man or no man, without any more will to admit a corrivall, then <hi>Caeſar</hi> to ſhift ſtakes with <hi>Pompey,</hi> or <hi>Alexander</hi> with <hi>Darius,</hi> or the true mother once to divide the child with the falſe mother, deteſting an <hi>Agrippa,</hi> that is but half perſwaded to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian and no further, like a Cake, half bak'd, or fleſh half boil'd, or halfe broil'd, occaſioning ſo much our Iriſh Fluxes: ſo in moralty, though I approve what <hi>Paul</hi> allowed <hi>Timothy,</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> Mother the ſad hearted, a little wine, as a little raine to refreſh the earth, not to bog it with too much, or ſo many cups from the grape (according to the old diſtinction) as tend to neceſſity, and to hilarity, yea to acuity to whet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten the wits of a heavy Dutchman, and to heat a cold Beotian braine, yet I diſlike a man to be half drunk, maudlin drunk, and but partly ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, as I diſtaſt a man that is but partly honeſt, and not down-right as <hi>Cato</hi> in Rome, and <hi>Phocion</hi> in Athens, and a woman that is ſuſpected to be too great a dancer with the Romane <hi>Sempronia,</hi> or too great a comrade, with young Gallants, like <hi>Augustus</hi> his <hi>Livia,</hi> and <hi>Julia,</hi> to be held abſolutely honeſt. But to trouble the by-ſtanders no more with this half-ſtaking Gameſter, I touch upon another, who hath oft troubled me.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>4. <hi>One drunken Tom Trouble-towne, or Troubleſome.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Wonderfull Linguiſt, tho no Artiſt; unleſſe that illiberall <hi>Ars bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendi,</hi> the art of drinking or drowning all arts and good parts like ſome Beuclarks in drink, as Pearles caſt into boggs, be an art, though as needleſſe as for a young <hi>Phaeton</hi> to help <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot, or a candle to help the Suns light, to as much purpoſe as for a pen-feathered, pride-puft ignorant arrogant Novice to intrude himſelf to gain ſoules, or rather ſilver from an aged, a powerfull, painfull, and gifted Divine, which were as though ſome <hi>Guſman</hi> or Gooſeman Juni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or, ſhould offer to help an old man, though a bold man, and ſpirited, to get children on his Brides Matrimoniall or Miniſteriall: This pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, to deſcant and deſcribe him in his peſtilent poſtures. A blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring blatrant blade he is, who cannot be content to be drunk in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, (as many a biting uſurer, a cloſe adulterer, an envious Snake, a ſilent Serpent, a covetous <hi>Euclio,</hi> a churliſh <hi>Nabal,</hi> a plotting Court <hi>Haman,</hi> a Camp'd <hi>Achitophel,</hi> are damned in hugger mugger, and go to the Devill their Father without any noiſe) but his brains once waſhed, and his tongue oyled with the bleedings of the Barley, the clack of a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161930:5"/>Water Milne, the ſtriking of the Jacks, the whirling of the wheels in a Clock, the ſcolding of two <hi>Xantippes,</hi> the prevarications of two So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſters in the Schooles, the word Tiltings of two Lawyers at the Bar, yea, the chatterings of Crowes in a wood, when their neſts are pulled downe, or the removall of a Court or a Camp, are not with more noiſe and diſturbance then drunken bluſterings, houtings and ſhoutings of this turbulent <hi>Tom Trouble-towne,</hi> which are more harſh then the noiſe of Dragons, the hallow tones of Biturnes, the ſhrill ſhreeks of Night-owles, or the loud Hones and Hubbubs of our clamorous Iriſh: but if theſe ſpeak him not fully, when he drinks fluently, the ſhouts which the old wives in <hi>Chaucer</hi> gave, and Dame <hi>Partlet</hi> the Hen, when the Fox carried <hi>Chanticleere</hi> the Cock to the wood, or the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciferations of the Carthaginean wives, when their children were ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, and carried pledges to Rome, ſcarce parallel the clamours and <hi>Sten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> voices, which this obſtreperous immorigerous troubleſome Tof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pot with his night-walking Nebuloes make, when their throats are deep ramm'd, and the barrells of their brains full charg'd with <hi>Bacchus</hi> his bolts: Oh they roare then as if in ſo many Pumps, they ſo deafe the ſnortings of Beares, the howling of Iriſh Wolves, and the barkings of all the Towne-Doggs, that it is not poſſible to ſteale a nap for them, ſo long as theſe Tarmagants roare; for my poor part, I had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heare a hundred bullocks of mine owne bellow, and a thouſand ſheep of mine owne bleat, then to have my ears taken up by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the commotion of their black <hi>Santos:</hi> and however ſome Zealiſts have rather delighted in an untuned Welſh Harp, or in a Scotch Bagpite, then in the bellowings out of an Ale-houſe into Cathedralls of ſome white and black-ſpotted Bulls of Baſan, (as they Satirically ſtigmatized them, and their unedefying Cantings to loud Organs,) yet to me nothing comes more harſh then the Reboations of theſe tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Trouble-townes, excepting to hear or ſee an ominous Owle or a fooliſh Moore Cock making a noiſe in an ill becomed uſurped cage, with the extruſion of a more-deſired, more-delighting, more-deſerving Nightingale, or an ignorant beardleſſe <hi>Symplicius</hi> with no more lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning then a Lay-man, flurting up as unwarrantably, unworthily, unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely into the Pulpit of ſuch a Divine extruded, as might be his Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor for gifts and years, to beat into his blockiſh braines both morality, Divinity, ſcience, conſcience, humanity and civility, with all all the blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterings of Sir <hi>John Barlicornes</hi> clamorous Clyents could not ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161930:5"/>me, as to ſoe or heare (what I heard at ſecond hand in Ireland) numerous Locuſts ſinging, and Frogs croaking from <hi>Po</hi> and <hi>Tyber</hi> in the chambers (as <hi>Quondam</hi> neere <hi>Thames</hi>) of Catholicall Grandees, and collapſed Ladies: yet in concluſion in the greateſt feared confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I ſhould be diſtreſſed, diſturbed, and diſtracted more then by all theſe, if I ſhould ſee or hear in this our white Albion (died red by the Pſeudodox, as once Jeruſalem, Antioch, and Damaſcus with the blood of the Orthodox) the raging of French and Spaniſh Bears, the roarings of Turkiſh Lions, the bellowings of Romiſh Bulls, (louder then from five Popes in Queen <hi>Elizabeths</hi> daies) and the howlings of Iriſh Wolves, called Rebells, in the deadly tones of the Moabites, up and to the ſpoiles of our Engliſh Iſraelites, let us fiſh our owne ends in their muddied yea bloodied waters, we are called in by a powerfull, and peſtilent party-coloured ſpotted Leopard, called <hi>Liberty of Conſcience,</hi> to plant every Nation and nature with more immunity and impunity then in Poland and Holland, his owne braine-bred Religion, though a blaſphemous <hi>Alchoran,</hi> or <hi>Thalumd,</hi> or <hi>Valentinus</hi> his renewed fond <hi>Aeones,</hi> or the reawakened dreames of <hi>Montanus</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla,</hi> or the deluding dotages of the Fratricellians, and Begnardines, and filthy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliſts and Adamites, which fired Italy and Germany; all theſe with a <hi>Warrantizabimus</hi> by the unerring ſpirit of Revelation without any Scripturian foundation, to be planted by power and poſſeſſion, to the ſupplanting of grace, peace, truth, and to the deforming a pretended and projected uneffected Reformation. But leaſt my porcupined pen pricking the galled hides of guilty hearts, ſhould ſo far trouble ſome zeal-drunk Zoiliſts, more then Drunkards trouble me, as not only to kick me out of a Church, as if innocent <hi>Philip</hi> from his owne pride to be poſſeſſed by ſome Herodian hot-ſpur, but to hurry me into <hi>Johns</hi> priſon, or <hi>Jeremiabs</hi> Dungeon, ſince <hi>procul à Jove, procul à Fulmine,</hi> it's good ſleeping in a warme skin, leaſt this troubleſome fellow by Law concluding <hi>in Ferio,</hi> trouble me as I have troubled him; I fly from him <hi>tanquam à cane &amp; angue,</hi> as from an unworm'd dog or ſnake, and bring on the Stage another, as though butter would not melt in his mouth. And that is</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>5. <hi>Drunken Agonethetas,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Maſter of the Revells, called M. <hi>Controler,</hi> who as peert as a Peermonger, and as ſpruce as a finicall Barber, will have either thing (which we ſcarce doe in our devotions) done in his drink in or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161930:6"/>der, though he cares as little for any ſolid Doctrine, as <hi>Aeſops</hi> Cock fora Pearle, or a dogg for a holy thing, which he ſleights, as the Gade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens did the beſt Doctor, and as our Gadders now into the Land of Nodd, nullifie our beſt Divines: yet he is wonderfull punctuall, for Diſcipline is obſerved more ſtrictly in his Taphouſes, then in ſome Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, or in the whilom Camps of <hi>Caeſar, Scipio, Hannibal, Sertorius, Charles</hi> the fifth, or the Germane <hi>Otho</hi> the 4. for even when he drinks with his comraigns as unmeaſurably as any hiſtorified. Tricongians and Novengians, or as <hi>Alexander</hi> at <hi>Celanus</hi> his Funerall, and when he dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth after full pots, as after full blowne pipes, the Engliſh Dance (now moſt in uſe in Courts, Camps, Countreyes and Cities) called, Paſſing meaſure, and Sellingers round, or the world upon wheels, yet he will be unmeaſurably angry and more hot then a Graves-end Toaſt, if all things be not done in meaſure: hence he acts more complements in drinking then Jeſuites and Friers in their ſtudied Cringings and duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings, or then the French, Spaniſh, or Italian in their Courtings, all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled with Court-holy water; ſo long as he can ſtand, he ſtands as much upon ceremonies in all houſes that are Ale-houſes, as ever they were ſtood upon, urged, preſſed and preſcribed in Biſhop <hi>Quondams</hi> daies, ere the altar-caſe ſo much altricated, did alter and halter too (<hi>quo Jure,</hi> I diſcuſſe not) in the reigne of Sir <hi>John Preſbyter,</hi> oppoſed by <hi>Hugh</hi> Sir <hi>Peter,</hi> and his Petreans: hence in all his punctuall poſtures acted to a haire, he vents all his invented and new minted comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall phraſes of <hi>Ditantoes, ſupernaculmus, upſefreeze, pro fas,</hi> cup-Waggins bearing up ſtiffe, winding up to the bottome, with his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant care of obſerving all the Statutes enacted in <hi>Bacchus</hi> his head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, brainleſſe, ſtaggering and party-coloured Senate, as amongſt the reſt: Firſt, that no blowne drink be left, it's loathed as ſome birds loath their eggs, if a Serpent do but breath on them. Secondly, healths as they go (like cauſes oft in Courts) by favour and friends, ſo they muſt be pledged perſonally, not (as ſome noble men ſay grace, and have ſome to venter hell for them) by any Atturneyes, Stewards and Deputies. Thirdly, ſome healths muſt go (as the globed world and the tottering times go) round, and like current coine paſſe from man to man, till the motion the potion begin againe, from <hi>terminus à quo,</hi> till it end in the <hi>terminus ad quem.</hi> Fourthly, though ſome Auditors and Schoolboyes in Churches care not for more then needs, being ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcionable, that they care not how little they have for money; yet as a
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161930:6"/>juſt meaſuring man that will have penniworths for his penny, he will have the black pot as brim full as he hath the liquids from it brainefull, blatherfull, and bellifull. Fifthly, he will have no drinking to the Tapſter, <hi>Chamberlaine,</hi> Drawer, or vulgar Officers, as once <hi>Tom Brown</hi> to his man. Sixtly, he ſo obſerves the Sex Feminine before the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine, being honoured in England, womens paradice, more then in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, Turky, Italy, or any Countrey their Purgatory, withall knowing that in moſt Countries Ducks will drink as much as Drakes, and Geeſe as much as Ganders, he enacts, that a woman muſt be drunk unto firſt, before a man, and ſometimes firſt drunk alſo. Seventhly, he looks that every man pledge what is drunk to him, not looking for any Lord-Dane or Lurdan to be pledge for him. Eighthly, he oft urgeth, that every man ſhall drinke as many cups as there be letters in the name of his abſent friend, whoſe health he drinks, for which he quotes a verſe of as much Antiquity or Iniquity, in <hi>Martiall,</hi> that <hi>Naevia ſex Cyathis ſeptem juſtina bibatur, Lide quatuor Ide tribus.</hi> Ninethly, every man muſt keep to his firſt man, ſouping of his full Can if he can, herein reſembling the Lion whoſe eye is never off him who darted firſt at him. Tenthly, he will not have it forgotten to call ever for a ſhot pot or come againe, after the reckoning, as a man of great reckoning in his drinke, though of ſmall account, being ſober; in ſuch exact punctualities he would turne all drinkings, as ſome lately (to their ſmall Laud be it ſpoken) all Church-Service into Ceremony, all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne ſpirituall Worſhip into Formality, as all Bottle-ale turnes into froath, moſt of Owles fleſh into feathers, and Banbury Cheeſe into pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings. But we have had enough of him and his Complements, we Summon next to the Bar,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <head>6. <hi>Drunken Dick the Gull-Gallant.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOt <hi>Dick mihi Muſa virum,</hi> for though this be a true Trojan, and a mad merry Grigg, though no Greek; yet he is not <hi>Virgils Dick,</hi> nor <hi>Dick</hi> of the old houſe of Lancaſter, nor <hi>Dick Eccleſiae;</hi> old <hi>Dick Bancroft</hi> of <hi>Canterbury</hi> in his time the <hi>Domine fac totum,</hi> that with a perillous pen writ his <hi>Theſes Periculoſae,</hi> perillous poſitions, like <hi>Liſama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Nicanor,</hi> and <hi>Owens Antipareus,</hi> parallelling Engliſh and Scottiſh Puritans (as <hi>Pluritans</hi> branded them) with State-firing Jeſuites; nor is it <hi>Dick Dulman</hi> who commenc'd at Dawes Croſſe, and to ſay no more of him, as if Dunſticall Husbands ſhould be inforced upon a relucting Brides, is huft and puft up into a Pulpit as his Pariſh croſſe or curſe:
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161930:7"/>nor is it <hi>Dick Litchfield</hi> the neat Cantibrigian Barber, whom <hi>Tom Naſh</hi> ſo trim'd in his Epiſtle againſt the three <hi>Harvies,</hi> but it is <hi>Dick</hi> the <hi>Gull-Gallant,</hi> the ſilken ſot, who though he have like a black pudding ſome ſuch excellent blood, mixt with his oatmeale and ſewet, as a widdow wiſhed for, in her matrimony, or matter of money, I mean great meanes to his generous or noble birth, ſuch Patrimony to his Parentage, as expoſe him not to the miſery of naked honours, with many of our Barons or bare-ones in both Clymes: yet nevertheleſſe he hath ſo many wide-throated Crowes about him to pluck his ſilver plumes yea to prey on him (and not as on other carrions) before he be dead, that they pluck him as bare as a birds taile, yea as naked as a Crecket, or Baboon, as our Iriſh Wolves lately ſhore and tore our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh ſheep; for as though an Elephant ſhould ſtoop to catch a mouſe, and an Eagle pounce a flie, yea as though <hi>Alexander</hi> in the Olympick Games, ſhould run or tilt with a Peaſant, not with a Prince, this moſt unworthy Gentleman, who never was candid nor Gentile, hath his wealth poſſeſt, like a cowards ſword, by ſuch a daſtard and dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Maſter, that playing at ſmall Games ere he ſit out, as if a Hawk ſhould keep airy with Buzzards, he conſorts himſelfe uſually with Cordions and Coblers, Rakehells and Raveners, Oaſtlers and Tapſters, Raggamuffins, and Tatergallians, Tipplers, and Tinkers, and all the Troup of traſh allied to the laſh: Theſe are <hi>delitias Domini,</hi> every one of them his <hi>vade mecum,</hi> his <hi>fidus Achates,</hi> his <hi>alter ego,</hi> his <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelphus,</hi> at the leaſt his Lackeys (till he lack) to attend him; yea his very ſpirits like <hi>Brutus</hi> his Ghoſt, which haunt him and follow him as cloſe as his ſhadow, he can no more ſhake them off then Doctor <hi>Fau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus</hi> his <hi>Mephiſtopholes:</hi> or <hi>Cardinall Creſcence,</hi> and <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> their Familiars in forme of black Doggs: in their deaths they cleave to him like burres, contrary to other Horſe-leaches, they will not fall off even when they are full, they wait on him like inferiour beaſts, called Courtiers and Penſioners to the Regall Lion, to feed upon his leavings, or rather upon his livings, he feeds theſe Spaniels which fawne upon him, with good lappings from the tap: then when theſe <hi>Stentors</hi> are as full of wine as Organ-pipes, and Bag-pipes of wind, they proclaime his worthleſſe worth further then the Birds of <hi>Sapho</hi> and <hi>Hanno</hi> let out of their cages, ſung the fictitious Dieties of their feeders, as loud as thoſe poore men whom the Duke of Savoy feaſted, as his Hounds, by which Papiſtically he hunted heaven, opened loud
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:161930:7"/>when he came amongſt them, with their <hi>God bleſſe the Founder,</hi> (and as his Steward, replied the confounders too;) and though theſe his Water-doggs like the Doggs of <hi>Actaeon,</hi> devoure this their great Maſter, and as <hi>Pharoahs</hi> lean kine eat up this fat one by degrees, yea though theſe inſatiable Gulphs ſwallow him quicke as it were another <hi>Codrus,</hi> downe their wide weaſands in ſome proportion, as then Whale did <hi>Jonas;</hi> at beſt, though theſe Cornvorants and Harpies prey on him, flocking after him like Vultures at the ſcent and ſmell of the blood of the grape, ſo eating into his lands and livings by gradati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as worms into the entralls, and Fleſh-wolves into the fleſh where they were bred and long fed, that at laſt his beſt meanes being ſpunged, as the beſt juice out of Oringes and Lemmans, in his purſe-conſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he growes as lank as a Grey-hound, or a ſhotten Herring, or as a jaded horſe ſo over-ridden, that he is run cleane out of his girts, like one <hi>Gabriel Archer</hi> once in the Towne of Maulton, or Mault-Towne, that was ſo guawne by theſe water rats in his golden mines of 1000. a year, as once <hi>Hatto</hi> of Mentz, and <hi>Popiel</hi> of Poland by land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats in their fleſh, that though his Father was Bayliffe of Buy-land, he came by ſuch Catterpillers his comraiges, ſo to be Duke of Sell-land, and at laſt to be Prince of No-land, that his beſt Taverns were water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprings, his Hoſt-Duke <hi>Humphrey,</hi> his Hoſteſſe mother Need, his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Beggars Inne, where many a lewd <hi>Leutulus,</hi> a prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> a profuſe Prodigall hath lodg'd both before him, and ſince after him: yet nevertheleſſe when my Gull-Gallant is amongſt ſuch potti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Peaſants as claw him like a Tyger, whilſt he waſheth their mouths, and oyles their throats, placed in the midſt amongſt them, as the Devill ſometimes in the ſhape of a beaſt amongſt Witches and Conjurers, being here the chiefe figure amongſt theſe Cyphers, the principall verb amongſt theſe Heteroclites, the Cock of the game amongſt theſe Famlerts, even crowing upon theſe dunghills; but chiefly the maine male Deere and Buck of the firſt head, with his ſilver hornes amongſt theſe Raſcalls, where he may be Sir <hi>Jack</hi> ſay all, and Sir <hi>ohn</hi> pay all, being here as <hi>Caeſar</hi> wiſhed, King and Corypheus over theſe Mole-hills, rather then a ſubject to mountaines. Oh! he is in his deſired Center, his Turk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h heaven, his Temple, his Elizian fields, his petty Paradiſe: but if it be his hard hap as he thinks, to ſtumble into better company, his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualls or ſuperiors, oh then he is as melancholy as a Hare or an Owl, as dogged as a <hi>Tymen,</hi> as Saturnall as once <hi>Brutus,</hi> as ſilent as a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161930:8"/>Birding Cat, or a Turkiſh Mute, as much frightned as frogs with light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and thunder, he dares no more ſpeake then <hi>Roſcius</hi> once before <hi>Gato,</hi> he fears as much to open his mouth as a black Bird to chatter, or Cranes to make any noiſe when the Hawke ſores over the one, and Eagles watch the other, as they fly over <hi>Caucaſus;</hi> oh, then he is in his reall Purgatory, he had rather be turning the wheel at Roterdam, yea <hi>Ixions</hi> wheeſe, or fill leaking tubs with <hi>Danaus</hi> daughters, or rowle <hi>Siſiphus</hi> his ſtone, or doe any other Herculean task that he could man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, then undergo the penance of converſing with any above his owne Sphere, from whom he flies further then <hi>Daphne</hi> in the Poet, from <hi>Apollo,</hi> or that young man in the Hiſtory from <hi>John</hi> the Divine, loving the company of Theeves more then his; with his good will he comes no nearer any better then himſelfe, then a Serpent to an Aſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, or to Iriſh ground, or then Spiders to Iriſh wood in Weſtminſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hall, where in no caſe they dare come to ſpin any catching webs for fat flies, though Doctor <hi>Didimus</hi> doubts it, and <hi>Scepticus</hi> doth diſcuſſe it, but I am ſure he flies from all generous and ingenuous ſociety as <hi>Moſes</hi> from kis rod turned ſerpent, <hi>quid piſcis in arido, Monachus in Mundo,</hi> he wonders what he ſhould doe amongſt ſuch more then a fiſh in the Forreſt, or a Monk out of his Cell amongſt ſeculars: and amongſt ſuch he ſhuts his lips as <hi>Graculus inter Muſas,</hi> unfit he ſhould jangle amongſt witty Gentlemen: ſo he ſhuts alſo his purſe, and binds it faſter then any man a ſcolding tongue, to ſuch good behaviour, that it lies quiet in his pocket and never ſtirrs: to get a farthing from him, unleſſe amongſt his owne froathy followers, were to get oyl out of a ſtone, or water out of a flint, or a penny from moſt Churches now in Troynovant to relieve diſtreſſed Hibernians, though roaſting us at lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gring fires, or if ought be wrung from him, as <hi>Neptunes</hi> Trident, or <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Mace out of their fiſts, for very ſhame not to be counted a hedger, this is as to wring the blood out of his noſe, he parts with it as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly as with his right eyes, or what is ſpent this way, he counts it miſpent as oyle ſpilt upon the ground; but hoping that though he have fed long on Widgins, Dotterills and Woodcocks, yet by change of diet, and a freſh aire removed from the bogs of baſe bagages up to the hills of holier ſpirits, and by a little Hellibore to cure his mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, his badneſſe, and many break-faſts of Rew mixt with thrift, he ſlſalt not hereafter break faſt, as he hath begun. Let us reflect more briefly on a ſpurious baſe brother of his, his Cozen Germane a Crow
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161930:8"/>of a rotten egge ſteept in wine Lees, or rather a hot ſpawne of the old Serpent the unclean ſpirit. And that is</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <head>7. <hi>Drunken Laurence, ali-aſs Luſty-guts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHoſe indictment to draw as favourably as I can, however when he is himſelfe, and hath on his conſidering cap, he is as ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continent as an <hi>Hippolitus,</hi> a <hi>Scipio,</hi> a <hi>Zenocrates,</hi> as though he fed much on <hi>Agnus, Castus,</hi> and ſallets of Lettice and Rew ſteep'd in drink, <hi>viris Venerem minuens, (Mulieribus addens)</hi> a great friend to Maſculine ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtity, and being unmarried, wanting wedlock waters to coole his fires, he improves as a Votary to <hi>Minerva</hi> and the Muſes the ordinary uſe of ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iccating Tobacco, and is put to his ſhifts of daily ſhifted ſhirts, yea of ſwimming in ponds and rivers, as S. <hi>Francis</hi> tumbled himſelfe naked in the nettles, and S. <hi>Dominick</hi> in the ſnow, <hi>ad reſtinguendam Venerem,</hi> to keep himſelfe chaſt by art, though not by nature; yet when he puts off his conſidering cap, and puts on his barly cap, as he begins to be a friend to <hi>Bacchus</hi> and <hi>Ceres,</hi> he ſhewes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe no foe to <hi>Venus,</hi> (as once her <hi>Adonis:</hi>) nay then as much as any of her Priap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ed Friers, or ſuch veſtall Nuns her Votaries as filled <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> Fiſh-pond with five hundred ſculls of dead Infants, or as Pope <hi>Joan</hi> who by the help of a Cardinall or carnall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oal'd a faire young Pope in the open ſtreet, (as the right Scarlet Whore indeed) leaſt the Papacy ſhould want heire males of her bodie unlawfully begotten, or as chaſt as that Cardinall in England who declaimed againſt the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages of Miniſters, when himſelfe was catched in bed with a Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bine that very night: this late <hi>Luſty Laurence, that Lancaſhire Lad,</hi> who had 17. baſtards in one year, if we believe his Ballad, after his Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſh and pot provender, is a ſtallion that neighs after every female Filly, every <hi>Phillis</hi> or Ill-is, he is in this hot humour, <hi>omnium horarum homo,</hi> as the Schoole-boy or Foole-boy miſconſtrued it, a man for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very whore, a <hi>Jack</hi> for every <hi>Gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> omnium mulierum vir,</hi> as <hi>Caeſar</hi> was called, proſtituting his <hi>Terentia, Servillia, Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>humia,</hi> and other Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſes, more then the late French <hi>Henry</hi> had; in this potting pickle: any fleſh fits his over-boyling pot, all is fiſh, or rather fleſh that comes to his net, from Madame to mad, he will uſe puddle waters to quench his fires, rather then none, any dirty pudding ſerves this hot whelp of <hi>Cerberus,</hi> he deſires to devoure more fleſh then any Minotaure, he would not ſpare an <hi>Ephigenia</hi> if ſhe come in his way, this Cub would lick and worry alſo leane lambs rather then none, no <hi>Jephtas</hi> daughter
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:161930:9"/>ſhould bewaile her Virginity, if ſhe would but bend her ſtring to his bow, for as he waxeth wild with wine, he would ſeale all his obſcame Letters with Virgins wax, and breake up every Bride Pie, ere it be well bak'd by <hi>Hymen,</hi> though it breed nought but wormes within him, and raw crudities in his drunken thirſt, he is ſuch a hot-ſpur, that he would loſe every Virgin <hi>Zone</hi> ere it be truly tied by <hi>Hymen,</hi> and good Sir <hi>John;</hi> in this hot pot poſture he will promiſe every maid marriage, and ſeale his promiſe if he can with his owne Image, though once ſeducing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny daughter of <hi>Eve</hi> to taſt the forbidden fruit, this hot Serpent caſts off the poiſoned tree, this Spaniel ſhakes off the water on the ſhore, when he hath uſed it to catch his deſired Duck, when he hath corrupted the wine, he throwes by the crack'd barrell, as Polititians throw by all ladders (if not break them, if Court-ladders for Princes) once climing to their own ends; his deſires after women increaſe with his wine, the fifty daughters of <hi>Danaus</hi> in one night deflowred by <hi>Herculès,</hi> nor the one hundred Sarmatian Virgins proſtituted by <hi>Proculus</hi> in one weeke, nay all the women in the grand Turks Seraglio would ſcarce ſattisfie the deſires of this fleſh-monger, this Mutton-worrier: this calfe ſo ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feits on change of paſtures, and he is ſo oft ſhaven with female Barbers, whoſe waters are heated with S. <hi>Anthonies</hi> fire, that <hi>vox populi</hi> cries, there went the haire away, ſo far and ſo faſt plucked off by a French P. called if you will a Pincer, that there is not a haire betwixt his head and heaven, but with this he ſhames ſo little, not caring one heire for his haires, that he counts it his (graceleſſe) grace to be neare a kin to Romes <hi>Caeſar,</hi> oft called, as a cooling card to his triumphs, <hi>Mechum calvum</hi> the bald Lecher, as alſo to the French <hi>Carolus calvus</hi> and <hi>Baldus</hi> the great Civilian. But I leave this Junior <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> or <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danapalus,</hi> or pale-aſſe <hi>in praeſenti</hi> tobe more wiſe <hi>in futuro,</hi> when the burnt child hath ſo oft felt the feared fire, otherwiſe unleſſe he mend his waies, ſhould I ſurvive him, I would write on him this Epitaph,
<q>
                     <l>This mad young colt deſerves a Martyrs praiſe,</l>
                     <l>For he was burned in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> daies,</l>
                     <l>The fewell to this fire, (oh, who would think it!)</l>
                     <l>In his owne belly burn'd when he did drinke it.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>But as I have no Genius for a Poet, I would not for a world the world ſhould know it, ſo I turne my Proſe in the next place to a Poet indeed, a doughty Poet in his drink,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="part">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:161930:9"/>
               <head>8. <hi>Drunken Don Quixo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ali-aſs Wittypoll.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>OF a ſudden by the fumes of <hi>Bacchus</hi> a muſhrump Poet, (as a Plebeian Enthuſiaſt in a trice by a Revelation dropped out of the clouds, or like a <hi>Pallas</hi> (pale-aſſe) borne out of a fictitious <hi>Jupiters</hi> braine, in his owne conceit or deceit, is a Muſhrump Preacher,) with his <hi>est Deus in nob is agitante caleſcimus illo, Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> yeeld to us our fires, <hi>Promethians</hi> be our Spirits, heaven inſpires, but to ſend your eyes after this Sir Ferdinando Faſh, this Furor Poeticus, however when he is himſelfe meer man, and no more, his Genius is obtuſe, and dull and heavy, as a great headed Oxe that needs the Goad, or as a Smith-field jade that needs the ſpur, yet heated with ſuch waters, as are extracted by fires from Limbecks of coldeſt Simples, he is preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in excelſis, he is hoiſted up as a ſquib into the aire, with ſuch cracks and flaſhes as would terrifie all the Buzzards that flock about him, and all the Ducks and Ganders that ſwattle with him in the ſame puddles or fuddles, <hi>Icarus, Dedalus, Simon Magus,</hi> our Engliſh King <hi>Blad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d</hi> never ſoared higher by Magicall or Artificiall wings, then he by the ſufflations of grinded and powdered Barly, hotter in his braines to blow up his inventions, then any Salt-Peter to blow up a Parliament-Houſe into the aire, for ſympathizing with his Predeceſſors <hi>Tom Naſh, George Peale, Kit Marlow, John Green,</hi> old <hi>Elderton, Churchard</hi> (buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Alectoes</hi> torch in the Church-Porch) fantaſtique <hi>Fenner,</hi> and the reſt of the pottizing Poetizing fraternity: he never is ſo good a Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſter, as when a pot-taſter, when he is as giddy with drink, as a Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummers Gooſe, then he ſwaggers more valiantly with a Gooſe-quill, then any <hi>Cline<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> or <hi>Damatas</hi> from the Bodkin to the pike upward, then he marcheth thorow any mans guts as it were with Gunpowder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termes, his pen pricks ſharper then a Porcupines, his ink is as ſtrong as his drink, it peirceth into a mans braines, in jerking <hi>Iambicks</hi> and pric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>Satyres,</hi> ſharper then the briſtles of a Hedge-hogg, it were able to make another <hi>Hipponax</hi> go hang himſelfe. Oh, how he then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ents Seſquipedalian words, how his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes are ſtronger then <hi>Aqua-fortis</hi> that eats into ſteel, how he ſpeaks <hi>lapldes &amp; Fulmina,</hi> ſquibs and fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>works, how his wits ſparkle like ſalt in the fire, he caſts them amongſt his Comraiges, as one <hi>Maples</hi> in <hi>Cambdens Britania</hi> ſaid, he was caſt amongſt Courtiers, as ſalt amongſt freſh Eels, to ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e them frisk, and dance without a piper: of all Hereſies now revived <hi>extremo ab orco,</hi> as from the loweſt held, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ow peſter the Church, as Locuſts from the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161930:10"/>bottomleſſe pit, as he hates moſt the Hereſie of the <hi>Aquarii,</hi> or water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drinkers, ſo he is very glad that it is not ſet abroach now amongſt the reſt; he holds this Axiome above any Article in the Nicene or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Greed, that <hi>nulla, ſcribuntur, Carmina aquae potoribus,</hi> that as good verſes come from Rurall Skinkers, as from our Hydro-Poets, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter drinkers, and he is verily perſwaded that however <hi>Tailour</hi> row in the water, yet when he ſhaped his beſt Poeticall ſhreds, his Muſe drunk wine out of the old bottells of the Tower: in briefe, lapping out of old <hi>Homers</hi> baſon, that <hi>Vinum Cos.</hi> which <hi>Homer</hi> drunk, though he doe not as exactly as <hi>Virgil</hi> imitate <hi>Homer,</hi> nor as our <hi>Chaucer</hi> and <hi>Spencer Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil,</hi> yet as <hi>Anguitur vini vinoſus Homerus,</hi> as <hi>Homers</hi> raptures ſmell of wine, ſo doe his Rapſodies with old <hi>Ennius nunquam niſi potus ad arma,</hi> he never poetizeth ſo vigorouſly, as when he poetizeth with his tip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pling tools, then <hi>ſecundi &amp; foecundi calices fecere deſertum,</hi> he quaffes <hi>elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> out of full cups <hi>pleno cornu,</hi> every Can is his <hi>Cornucopia, poſt ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum vinum loquitur ſun lingua Latinum,</hi> he with his wine ſips wits and words ſo ſtrong as fill him fluent with his Latine Tongue, his <hi>pinta Maior,</hi> and <hi>pinta Minor,</hi> this pot and that pinte makes him more fluent then <hi>Hector pinta</hi> upon <hi>Eſa:</hi> theſe are to him for words and phraſes more then either <hi>Couper</hi> or <hi>Minſhaw,</hi> or <hi>Calepine,</hi> or <hi>Holyoake</hi> or <hi>Rider,</hi> or <hi>Thomas Thom-aſs</hi> or any other Dictionaries: if he be to hammer out any wordy work indeed, he never ſtands muſing on the matter, with his <hi>Pierides Muſae,</hi> nor doth invocate his great Pan, a great Can, out of which he ſteals a hearty draught, elevates his ſoring raptures as high as <hi>Parnaſſus,</hi> his <hi>Helicon</hi> is only to Hell-it-on, as we ſay in Yorkſhire, and power in ſpirited liquor which will cauſe him powre out ſpirited lines; but at laſt leaveing this Junior <hi>Randoll; Pupill</hi> to <hi>Ariſtippus</hi> to read his red Latice Lectures, I take a <hi>Synopſis</hi> with a little more brevity on</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="part">
               <head>9. <hi>Drunken Spermologous.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Bird of the ſame feather, a word-minter, a <hi>Coriatized Odcomb,</hi> a meer verball <hi>Windy-bags,</hi> above any mountbank, Emperick, or <hi>Albumazar,</hi> a coiner of fuſtian phraſes in <hi>Bacchus</hi> his forge, in ſuch proud pittied and derided follies, ſtraining to be eloquent, as the fabled Frog ſwelled to be an Oxe, in his Inkcorniſme Rombiſmies; Gallymaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freyes, and <hi>Omnigetherums,</hi> of Engliſh and Latine, and ſome ſhreds of French too, and in his Gibberiſh in Welſh and Corniſh, which he would have to go for Greek, mixt alſo together in ſuch a drunken hotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potch
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161930:10"/>of affected rope Rhetorick, as makes him as ridiculous as a jang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Jay, or prating Parrot, which talks at randome ſhe knowes not, nor ſhe cares not what; all his diſcourſe, as too courſe for any judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſolid eare, being held onely to keep a fitting Symetry with Sir <hi>Simon Simple,</hi> and Sir <hi>Gregory Non-ſence,</hi> ſuch companions as moſt of our zeale-drunk Plebeians take with them up into moſt of our uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped Pulpits, which they leave as fouly polluted with ignorance and arrogance, as Foxes, Fowmarts, Weaſells and Poulcats leave ill ſmells behind them where ever they come: but having enough of this <hi>Windy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baggs,</hi> permitting him to fly with the wings of his wits, fantaſtically feathered, as an Ole in an evening, I make as bold as welcome, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcant a brother of his,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="part">
               <head>10. <hi>Drunken Phylautus,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHo double drunk with ſelfe-conceit, as well as wine, he is no ſooner a note above <hi>Ela</hi> in his maultified mentall muſick, but then eſpecially, he conceits all his Geeſe to be Swans, his Capons Cocks, his Goats Sheep, his Rats Rabbits, and his Glow-worms blazing Stars; and that he, and not that whilom fantaſtike <hi>Parſons,</hi> nor yet old <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> is King of the Fayries, or faire-eyes, the great Duke of Eutopia, and the grand Seignior of all that Land, within the Orb of the Moone, which the Authour of the Lunatick Moon-book Mathematically and Suppoſititiouſly deſcribes unto us: I muſt confeſſe, when I obſerve the ſtrange humours and conceits of his out-weaned worthleſſe ſelfe, which the Devill and drink infuſeth into this proud drunken foole, and note all the addle idle eggs which <hi>Bacchus</hi> hath in his braine, I leſſe marvell, that a poor, ſilly, ſimple, vulgar, Mechanick Ideot drunk with meer blind and bewitching zeale, and ſelfe-conceit of his ſuppoſititious and imaginary gifts, ſhould conceit himſelfe to be as legall, as able, as gifted as called a Preacher, as any of the Sons of the Prophets, on whom God hath redoubled, as the ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> on <hi>Eliſha,</hi> the ſpirit of preaching, and whom the Church hath called to the Function of a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. But being as much aſhamed, that Doctor <hi>Carter, Carrier, Currier, Brewer, Dunce,</hi> and <hi>Dulman,</hi> ſhould preſume to equallize Doctor <hi>Worth, Wiſdome,</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> as that <hi>Cumanus</hi> his Aſſe ſhould jet it in a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons skin, or that any <hi>Midas</hi> ſhould as an emblame of a ſottiſh Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, preferre <hi>Pans</hi> harſh poore pipe, before <hi>Apolloes</hi> melodious Harp: I ſound retreat to ſtand, and obſerve another ſtrange Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanalian,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="part">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:161930:11"/>
               <head>11. <hi>Drunken Sip-Sobrius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>A Strange Hermaphrodite, who in one houre changeth from drunk to ſober, as a Raven in few daies changeth from white to black in her hatching neſt, and as a Hare and <hi>Hiena</hi> are ſaid in one yeare to change from male to female, and as <hi>Camerarius</hi> in his <hi>Hiſtoricalls, Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lart</hi> and <hi>Wolfius</hi> in their <hi>Admiranda,</hi> inſtance in many changing Sexes, from men to women, as the witches in Livonia in the moneths of June and July, are ſaid to change from women into wolves: ſo this <hi>Sip-So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brius,</hi> as though rope-maker-like he went backward and forward, as ſome men and women with their words and works, he is in a very trice both drunk and ſober: what operation the diverſified muſick of <hi>Timotheus</hi> had to cauſe <hi>Alexander</hi> firſt to put on his Armour to fight as a Lion, then to calme him as mild as a Dove, or to turne him to a ſad melancholy, and then by other ſtrains to be joviall, me thinks the ſame worke hath drink in this Camelionized metamorphoſed Mault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worme, Peernizing him from drunk to ſober, ſooner then all ſolid preaching and powerfull oratorious perſwafions can work upon the intoxicated braines of a mad Plebeian Enthuſiaſt, to turne him from a zeale-drunk ſelf-conceited Teacher, to his owne former garb of a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber Tradeſman, which being almoſt as impoſſible as to conjure down a Devill into hell, his old Center, or to gather the diſperſed winds into <hi>Aeolus</hi> his bag againe: I leave him, and being bold to ſtraine curteſie with the Clergie as well as the Laity, I make up my Browne Dozen with</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="part">
               <head>12. <hi>Drunken Clericus, or Simplicius.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Countrey Vicar, who to his meat muſt have liquor, as well as others, even as oft as a Lemman to his fauce, as Mr. <hi>Howard</hi> told Queen <hi>Mary</hi> when ſhe took away wines from the Clergie, yea though many call him Sir <hi>Iohn</hi> Lack Latine, yet with his good will this <hi>Senior Immerito,</hi> will not lack liquids; in which humour, <hi>pace tanti viri,</hi> I have oft ſeen I muſt confeſſe, even learned Latinizing <hi>Beuclark</hi> himſelfe, and ſometimes <hi>Ingenioſo,</hi> a Maſter of Arts, as well as <hi>Tripes</hi> the prevarica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Sophiſter, or Ariſtippized <hi>Randoll,</hi> or <hi>Iunior,</hi> and <hi>Senior vix Sanior Bachalaurius, Baculo, non Lauro dignus,</hi> with many fellowes as right good fellowes in Colledges, as <hi>Noah</hi> was a good Lawyer, <hi>Butler</hi> a good Phyſitian, and <hi>Paracelſus</hi> a good Chimiſt: and although that Carp-fiſh that <hi>Ariſtarchus</hi> or ſtark-aſs, that Tymoniſt, that Miſanthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt, yea that dogged <hi>Cynick,</hi> if not formall Phariſee, that <hi>Samet</hi> more
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161930:11"/>preciſe then wiſe brain-ſick Zealiſt, who will not only friske away from the beſt gifted Preacher, as a young Heifer with a tick on her taile, out of a freſh paſture, leaping over hedges, or as a wild Deere or Raſcall trips over the mountaines at chop of a Beagle, but will ſhoot his fooles bolts at him, that he is a friend to Publicans or Sinners, if he ſee him but <hi>(ſemel in anno ridens Apolle) raro aut nunquam,</hi> now and then in an Inne or Tavern, though perhaps upon as lawfull an occaſion as the Spies had who lodged in <hi>Rahabs</hi> Inne in Jerico, or as <hi>Joſoph</hi> had when he took up his lodging in Bethlem: I ſay ſuch a criticall or hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall cenſor, had need to have either his braines took out and waſht with ſalt and ſage, or his inwards purg'd from the over-flowings of gall and ſwellings of the ſpleen: yet nevertheleſſe as I would have all of <hi>Levies</hi> Tribe to ſteere from the rocks of the leaſt offence, becauſe a little mote is ſeen in their eyes, a little mire on their coat, and that which is drunkenneſſe (ſaith a Father) in others, is ſacriledge in them; ſo for my part, <hi>ſepe bilem, veſtri movere tumultus,</hi> it oft ſtirres up my paſſion, as well as compaſſion, to ſee ſo many excellent good parts, pains, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and wits not only waſhed, but as once <hi>Noahs</hi> for a time drowned in drink, at leaſt ſoiled as Pearls in a quagmire; as they tax the finnes of others, ſo the obſerving vulgars taxing ſome of them, not for legall uſing, but too much abuſing both <hi>Bacchus</hi> Tobacco, and all ſtrong li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quids in their quiffs and their quaſſs, that they oft drink till there be no wine in their pots, wits in their pates, nor wealth in their purſes, in moſt Climes, ſome ecclipſing and clonding all the beſt of their ſhining gifts by the interpoſition of a lunatick watery Plannet, many more commonly then commendably taking their liquors till their liquors take them, as the Lobſter catch'd the Cat, when the Cat thought to catch the Lobſter, and as the Waſp catch'd the Welſh-man by the noſe, when her thought to eatch the Waſp by the laps of her yellow Jerkin: carouſing as freely all ſorts of ſtrong liquids, whether Der<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Ale, or Nantwich Whiskings, or Briſtow Beer, or Gloceſterſhire Sydar, or Worceſterſhire Perry, or Welch Meath and Metheglin, or French Claret, or Germane Renniſh, or ſweet Muſcadine, and Malmſie, or Spaniſh Sack well mixt with ſugar, as zeale with diſcretion, all quaft as freely as the Turks their Coſſa, the Graecians their Falern, and <hi>Vinum Cos,</hi> the Iriſh their Aqua vitae, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſque bangh,</hi> or the Ieſuites in Paris their <hi>vinum Sorbonicum &amp; Jeſuiticum;</hi> I reſolve to tell you the truth, (as giving you thirteen to the Dozen) to Anatomize</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="part">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:161930:12"/>
               <head>13. <hi>Drunken Tom Tell-troath.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TO give you the full or foole of him, he is one that either never read or never underſtood nor regarded <hi>Alberius magnus,</hi> that great All-beard, nor <hi>Wickerus,</hi> nor <hi>Baptiſta Porta,</hi> nor <hi>Levinus Lemnius de ſecretis,</hi> nor <hi>Cardan de occultis,</hi> nor any writings of hid things and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, which he no more heeds nor obſerves to keep, then moſt in this falſe and ſickle age, heed or keep faith, truth, honeſty, juſtice, cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit or conſcience, which moſt of them are fled to heaven to complaine of their want of entertainment upon earth. Of all others he is unfit to be a Secretary as a woman, who for the moſt part writes Romane hand, few of that ſex Secretary; everſince <hi>Fulvia</hi> bewrayed the ſecrets of <hi>Cataline, Martia</hi> of <hi>Comodus, Dalilah</hi> of <hi>Sampſon,</hi> or <hi>Fabia</hi> of her husband <hi>Fabius,</hi> concerning that which <hi>Augustus</hi> revealed to him of adopting <hi>Tyberius</hi> to be his ſucceſſor in the Empire, what ever he knows muſt out at one hole or other: were I a King, and he as familiar with me, as <hi>Schoogan</hi> with the French King, I would make him of my pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, rather then of my counſell, leaſt he kept it no better then a ſive or a riddle keeps water: what I would have known or divugled, I would tell him, he would vent it ſooner in his cups, then if I told it in a Barbers ſhop, a Milne, a Market, a Schoole-houſe, amongſt boyes, a Bake-houſe amongſt wenches, or at a Gooſeups feaſt, onely commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding one good thing in him, (as once one juſt act in <hi>Cambiſes</hi>) I leave him, and that is, that he never lets any ſecrets rot in his mouth, (as a Romane once Apologized) to cauſe him to have a ſtinking breath. But leaſt we hunt him and his fellowes out of breath, for their being foxt like Foxes till they ſtink again, giving them a breathing time to repent, and to weep, if it be but drunken tears in their Dog-ſick vomits, we reprieve them till the next Seſſions, where more of their fellowes, God willing, ſhall be arraigned with them at <hi>Bacchus</hi> his Barre: and as we find ſome dozen and a halfe more of them guilty, after whipping and ſtripping, they ſhall have a ſhipping into Drunkallia, or the Iſle of Gulls, for their too bold and baſe abuſing of Sir <hi>John Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly corne,</hi> and M. <hi>Mault</hi> his bearded ſon, and M. <hi>Barly-broth,</hi> his braine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe daughter, as in a manner unworthy, till they mend their manners, to ſtay or ſtagger any longer in the Iſle of Man.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
